Hello everyone. Welcome back.
Today we're going to talk
about some of the fundamental
key and core concepts of
respiratory physiology.
So here it is. I'm
Vishwar Ajagopavan. I'm
an associate professor
from the biomedical
sciences and here are
the learning objectives.
So you're comparing
and contrasting the
relationships between lung
volumes and capacities.
Discussing spirometry and its
limitations in measurements
of lung volumes and capacities
and the methodologies
associated with determining
residual volume and
function residual capacity
and then extrapolating these
volumes capacities with
respect to common pathologies
such as obstructive and
restrictive lung diseases and
then talking about dead
space to talk about regions
of the lung that don't
participate in the gas exchange
and then how to measure dead
space. Major objectives.
Let's dive in. So before
that overall what are
the functions of the
respiratory system? We're
not going to talk
about all these in this
session. There are other
lecturers together will
raise you to understand
all the functions of the
respiratory system but here
we're to talk about a certain
aspect but in general one
is major function is the
exchange between the atmosphere
and the blood and the end
organ and the end tissue
and tissues and cells okay
and then we have protecting
against inhalatory substances
and pathogens etc
smoking intentionally or
unintentionally the harmful
materials are you know fire you
know fire anything for that
matter any particles that
can be stopped by the inner
layer of the respiratory
system it tries to protect
as much as possible beyond
that it goes in now acid
and base homeostasis that's
another one that's another
major one right especially
in in collaboration with
the kidneys and the lungs
plays an important role and
then vocal control as well
all right so we're going
to talk about the key four
major processes not all four
but what are the four major
processes one is ventilation
diffusion transport
regulations what's ventilation
ventilation is about inflow
and outflow of air between
the atmosphere and the
lung alveoli okay and so
that's the major aspect of
ventilation now diffusion
is about the external aspect
of respiration it's a gas
exchange between the alveoli
and blood right and transport
is the transport of gases
we the blood stream
transport of oxygen carbon
dioxide in the blood and body
fluids you know to and fro
the body tissue cells and
regulation is about central
regulation by the brainstem
and this also is internal
respiration which is the
respiration happening the gas
exchange between blood
and the cells and then the
cellular level respiration
interest intercellular
intracelular respiration which
is a mitochondrial electron
transport but for our purposes
we're going to highlight
pretty much on ventilation
here okay this is just
an overview for you all
right so the first part lung
volumes and capacities what
are they pulmonary function
test is a major way by which
the lung clinics try to
understand what's the status
of the patient's lungs.
So in addition to
history, physical exam,
radiology, etc., this is
an important non-invasive
way to help determine
the overall lung health.
And these tests
determine, you know,
in addition to lung volume
capacities, they also help
us understand the rate of
airflow the quality of alveolar
gas diffusion and so on
and they are already part
of pulmonary medicine but
we will focus on the key
fundamental concepts here
okay lung volumes what are the
lung volumes um the basic
lung volumes are the tidal
volume that you see the
curve let me put my um get my
cursor okay see if it works
yeah all right title volume
right title volume is here
title volume is this this
curvy curvy this curvy
one title volume includes
inspiratory and expiratory
they're about the same volume
about so we will look into
the numbers all right in a
moment so tidal volume both
inspiratory and expiratory
this is normal breathing
as we are now you're now
sitting comfortably wherever
you are and you're breathing
this is tidal volume now
when you take a deep breath
for any reason okay sigh
of relief or um whatever
reason you're taking a deep
inspiratory walk inspiratory
breath you're doing um yoga
or whatever that deep
breath is the inspiratory
reserve volume how much
voluntarily you're able to go up
take in breathe in that's
been inspiratory the opposite
how much you are able to
expire voluntarily right
I'm demonstrating here so
that expiratory voluntary
expiratory reserve volume
that is this this that is this
and that's the that's the
human limit now beyond that
there there is air in the
lung there will be air in
the lung that we cannot expel
how much ever we try okay
how much ever we try there
is some amount of air that
is called the residual
volume so that's the air that
cannot be blown out no matter
how hard we try okay all
right so so fundamentally
tidal volume inspiratory
reserve volume expiratory
reserve volume and residual
volume we will look we will
extend this a little bit to
capacities what are capacities
so what we saw so far
is tidal volume inspiratory
reserve expiratory reserve
and residual now when you
combine couple of these at
a time right so when you
combine inspiratory with
expiratory not expiratory when
you combine inspiratory with
the time volume that total
volume is called inspiratory
capacity this is our ability
from baseline okay so
this is at this point
inspiratory is a point where we
have normally breathed in
and then on top of it you're
breathing extra that extra
is mister reserve now
this extra plus regular is
inspiratory capacity now this
extra inspiratory plus
regular plus extra expiratory
right you combine IRV
inspiratory reserve volume tidal
volume TV and ERV expiratory
reserve volume all this
combined becomes vital
capacity and then now if you
go down expiratory reserve
and residual okay so this is
the total amount of air that
can and cannot be expelled
from the lungs those that
are sitting inside and
those that you can push out
force push that is functional
residual capacity and finally
everything you combine
everything becomes the total
lung capacity total lung
capacity which is breathable
and something that you
can and cannot everything
combines total lung capacity
all right we'll move on we
will look at it again in a
different way to help us
understand so so we have the
at the end of normal
inspiration right this is normal
inspiration at the end of
normal inspiration this is
at the end of normal
expiration so each one is tidal
volume the same volume is
and here when you take a deep
breath after your end of
normal inspiration that's
you reach this point of end
of maximal inspiration and
then this volume is
inspiratory result volume this
is tidal volume this is
inspiratory result this is
tidal this is tidal and
then you come here tidal
and And then this is, from
here to here is, my bad,
here to here is
expiratory reserve volume.
And then you reach
the point of end of
maximal expiration,
beyond which you cannot.
Now we combine these,
we already saw in the
last slide, IC equals
VT plus IRV, VC equals
VT plus IRV, and so on.
And look at this below,
the normal approximate
tidal volume is 500 ml.
These things you can remember.
Some of these would be
important for you to remember.
It also gives you a good mental
image and idea about this.
Inspirative reserve is
about 3,000 ml. Expirative
reserve is less than that.
A third of inspirative
reserve is what you can
expel. You can breathe in
a lot more volume than
what you can breathe out.
Right? That's interesting.
And then there is
residue volume which is
more than a liter that's
sitting there inside the
lungs that's just sitting.
Now the capacity
capacity, inspiratory
capacity, when you combine
it, 3500 vital capacity,
combine all 34500.
Functional residual is
2200, and this is total
lung is 5.7 mL, right?
Okay, that's informative.
Let's move on.
Now, just a different
perspective of understanding
it, the inspiratory capacity
is the maximum moment of
air that can be inspired
following normal expiration.
When you think of it
you'll understand this.
Then the maximum,
what's vital capacity?
Sometimes called forced
vital capacity. It's
the maximum moment of
air that can be expired
after following a
maximum inspiration.
Maximal expiration after
a maximum inspiration.
That's vital capacity, a
forced vital capacity. And
the functional acid capacity
is, you already know,
RV plus ERV, is the amount
of air that's remaining in
the lungs following a
normal expiration. After you
normally breathe out what
is sitting inside that's
the functional residual
capacity volume and system
is relaxed okay so that's
and then total lung capacity
is some of all the volumes
you've heard that and
then the same thing but
you can look into this that
lung volumes these are four
non overlapping components
and these are some of the
two or more components
are overlapping so non
overlapping so one doesn't
overlap with one another
but the capacity do overlap.
For example total and
capacity overlaps everything
right and inspiratory capacity
overlaps both combines
both inspiratories volume
and title volume and so on.
So again it's a similar
thing that we saw but
to refresh to keep
you know taking home
this message because this
is an important figure.
Questions can come
in from this as well.
Any learning objective
questions can come. This is
one such important learning
objective from which questions
can come all right i'll
give you some sample
questions too okay now
functional residual capacity we
saw functional residual capacity
right what is functional
residual capacity it's a
combination of rb plus e
rb residual volume plus
excretor is a volume okay
why do we talk about it it's
relevant in both physiology
and pathology physiologically
first is pathology
here so from normal standing
position to supine position
there is a change in FRC
how does it change and in
ascites when there is fluid
collected in the abdomen
excessive and then when
there is paradoxical movement
in these scenarios there
is decrease in functional
residual capacity okay
functional residual capacity
decreases you'll see two more
examples one in pregnancy
in pregnancy what happens
as an example the FRC hand
total link capacity reduces
why because the compression
of the diaphragm your
the the diaphragm gets
compressed because there
is a lot more by the uterus
right and then the tidal
volume increases tidal volume
increases by 32 percent to
40 40 percent and then that
gives an increase in
pulmonary ventilation but the
functional residual capacity
has to reduce and we will
talk about this minute
ventilation in next session
but this is necessary
the the modification, the
adjustment in functional
residual capacity is necessary
to meet the increased oxygen
requirement of the body.
And obesity, similar idea,
there, the expirative reserve
volume, functional
residual capacity,
total incapacity, all
these, especially FRC
and TLC will reduce
due to the mass load of
adipose tissue surrounding
the ribcage and
abdomen. and there is
elevated intra-abdominal
pressure that can be
transmitted to the chest.
So these are some of the
conditions where you can see
modification change in FRC
and particularly decrease.
Now let's move on to the next
major concept of measuring
this using spirometry.
What's spirometry? Spirometer
is measures the volume of
air that's expired during
a forceful and complete
expiration after a maximum
inspiration so maximum
inspiration and then forceful
and then the volume of air
is measured that is you
know expired during the
forceful and complete expiration
after a maximum inspiration
now technically speaking
you don't have to you know
memorize how is it actually
done the itty-gritty
details but I'm just giving
you a little bit of you
know idea and nose clip is
placed used to seal the
nostrils to prevent air leakage
from the nose and then the
subject must place their
tips tightly around the
spirometer mouthpiece as you
see in this figure and then
here and then the subject
or patient is asked to breathe
so the subject must place
their lips tightly around
the spirometer mouthpiece
and breathe normally for a
few breaths and after the
normal breathing the
individual is asked to inhale
as deeply as possible and then
exhale as hard as possible
deep inhalation hard
exhalation this process is
repeated at least three times
until reproducible results
are accept a record. Now
this spyrometer consists
of a drum inverted over a
chamber of water with the
drum counterbalanced by
weight. If the, you can see
those in the figure, if the
drum is, so in the drum is a
breathing gas usually air
or oxygen and tube connects
it to the mouth with the
gas chamber etc and when
the person breathes into and
out of the chamber the drum
will rise and fall and an
appropriate recording is
measured so it's a breathing
that moves the chamber,
the drum actually
rises and falls.
Okay with that idea on the
right side you're seeing
the same figure that you
saw before the spirographic
record that's taken IRE,
ERV and RV and so on the
velocities sorry velocities
excuse me capacities and
volumes all right residual
volume that's there in
the bottom so what's residual
volume residual volume
we saw is the air that's
sitting in that's not
voluntarily breathable right
so spirometry is about a
voluntary breathing in and
out which means you cannot
measure the residual
volume it's necessary and
important in multiple
conditions to know so how do we
measure residual volume all
right let's get in that.
A couple of methods
are there and the main
method that's more
accurate or probably
most accurate is whole
body plethysmography.
Whole body plethysmography
how is it done? In a
patient or subject is placed
seated in a closed body
box it looks like you know
English ancient styled
phone booth which doesn't
exist anymore I guess.
So the subject sits
inside in the transparent
so we can see how
the patient is doing.
Then we can measure the
thoracic gas volume based
on Boyle's law. What's
Boyle's law? Long time ago you
would have learned P1 V1
equals P2 V2 at constant
temperature and we will
see more in detail about
this law in the next session.
All right so now this
pathismography, back to
that, the subject is asked
to sit in a closed box
with large windows and then
they'll be asked to wear
a nose flip and asked to
take short and shallow
breaths to a mouthpiece when
it's blocked for a few
seconds, forced. So PFT labs
will offer will use, they
can use other tests as well
but this is an important
test. So So after period
of tidal breathing, the
spirometer is closed at
end expiration, and the
patient breathes against it.
Changes in pressure at the
mouthpiece are recorded.
And as the patient
exhales, the volume of the
thoracic cavity can be
calculated by recording
the change in pressure
of the entire chamber.
That's just to give you
an idea how it works.
And it's a pretty accurate,
you know, test, but it's
also relatively, I guess,
expensive than the other
methodologies so but once
the FRC once the function
the residual volume and the
functional residual capacity
has been measured using
one of the three methods
that we will see then
then we can calculate
tidal volume and total
lung capacity but
let's see yeah so that's
about plethysmography
then comes our nitrogen
washout the nitrogen
washout This is a test
based on nitrogen that makes
up 78% of atmospheric
air, right, the majority.
And the subject
breathes through a two
-way valve, as you
see in the figure.
David is there.
So this subject, the
patient, is made to breathe
through a two-way valve
connected to 100% oxygen on
inspiration and a collection
spirometer on expiration.
Now, the spirometer
measures the volume of air
and the fraction of
nitrogen. So both the volume
of air and the fraction
of nitrogen is measured
that's expired with each
and every breath. So every
expired breath, this spirometer
is going to measure the
volume of air and the fraction
of nitrogen. Nitrogen.
Hope I said nitrogen.
The test is complete
once the fraction of
nitrogen goes below one
and a half percent
for three consecutive
breaths and then the
initial amount of nitrogen
in the lungs must be,
look at the formula,
then we need to know the
initial amount of nitrogen in
the lungs and then that
must be equal to the total
amount of nitrogen exhaled
and thus the FRC can then we
can calculate the FRC. so
how do we calculate FRC okay
let's move you can actually
see the formula there
right FRC is volume exhaled
times concentration exhaled
concentration nitrogen
and then divided by the
concentration of initial alveolar
nitrogen so this information
will be used to measure
so if you're given some of
these parameters you should
be able to do you know the
math and be able to identify
the missing parameter.
Helium dilution,
another methodology.
Helium dilution, how
does it work? So first
it will help us detect
the, a spirometer is
present there. A
spirometer of known volume
is filled with air
that's mixed with helium.
The helium is not observed
across capillary across
alveolar capillaries right
so the helium the room air is
mixed with helium at a known
concentration excuse me
and then before breathing
from the spirometer the person
expires normally and then
at the end of expiration
the remaining volume in the
lungs is equal to the FRC.
At this point the subject
immediately begins to breathe
from the spirometer and
the gases of the spirometer
mix with the gases of the
lungs and consequently the
helium becomes diluted by
FRC by the FRC gases and
the volume of the FRC can be
calculated from the degree
of dilution of the helium.
So don't worry you know
too much if you have not.
What's more important is the
following the c1 v1 equals
c2 times v1 plus v2 so
note that the this formula
here so your goal is to find
one of the volumes let's
call the v2 as the functional
residual capacity here
I've called it as functional
residual capacity from
which you will measure the
residual volume so c1 v1
and then you rearrange the
formula that comes second
year you get the second
step the c2 goes there as in
the denominator and then
v2 and v1 is here you move
it on the other side v1
becomes negative so v2 is this
formula now now v2 is the
functional residual capacity
and then you rearrange
if you want based on the
common factor so anyway
you have you are given the
initial helium volume and then
initial helium concentration
and then the final helium
concentration and then
the ERV now this will when
you calculate and do the
numbers your FRC will be you
can pause and do your math
you can and then resume
I'll tell you the answer
now the answer is three zero
five zero ml okay and then
residual volume how do
you calculate the residual
volume I will leave this as
a little extra homework for
you it's not hard you
should be able to and try to
go back to the definition
of residual volume and you
will get the answer so
this is function residual
capacity all right let's move
on in the interest of time
okay let's clear this force
residual capacity excuse
me force vital capacity
which is the same as vital
capacity, but after a rapid
exhalation, after a maximal
inhalation. So maximum
inhalation and then, boom,
it's a rapid expiration.
Okay, here the same curves,
but emphasizing on the
forced vital capacity or the
vital capacity. Now, at the
first second, right, at the
first second, whatever you
are expiring, that's called
forced expeditory volume,
okay, forced expeditory
volume at one
second. And then
the 25 to 75% data,
it's 25 to 75%, that is
another important parameter,
we will talk about
that probably in a bit.
So here what you
need to know, forced
expiratory volume,
FEV1, what is that? It's
one of the simplest
tests of lung function,
it's a forced
expiration after a full
inspiration. Again,
forced expiration
after full or
maximum inspiration.
And it's known especially
in primary care
clinics when patients
are there for
evaluation of chronic
dyspnea, for instance.
Now, again, refreshing
what's forced
vital capacity in
a different way.
Forced vital capacity is a
maximum volume of gas that
can be exhaled as forcefully
and rapidly as possible
after full maximal inhalation.
and FEV1 important clinically
important parameter FEV1
is the in the first second
this is the volume of
air that's expired in the
first second during maximal
expiratory effort so when you
look at different patients
FEV1 the first to second
volume of air that's expired
then you can get good amount
of information as to what
kind of pathology they may
be suffering we'll talk
about that in a bit FEV1 by
FEC the ratio right ratio
of FEV1 here this is a FEV1
and then this is FVC this
ratio the percentage of the
of this which is expired in
the first second this is this
ratio and in a healthy
patient this is approximately
in the 70% range okay so
let's move on right so far
we have seen the lung volume
capacities and spirometry
let's talk about some
pathologies right that's fun COPD
well not really fun for
the patient but for our
understanding we will learn
a lot more from the patient
scenario COPD chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease very
important set of patients
use you can see a lot when
if you are in the pulmonary
clinic even in you know other
places as well so these
patients can be easily fatigued
they can go to frequent
respiratory infections use
of accessory muscles to
breathe they'll be using and
what are those accessory
muscles we will see in
the next session okay
orthopnea, core pulmonary
and then thin appearance,
wheezing and then
personal breathing, that's
a cough, barrel-shaped
chest is a classic feature
of chronic obstructive
pulmonary disease and
then dyspnea, difficulty
in breathing and then
prolonged expiratory time,
digital clogging, so it's a
classic patient we've here
okay what happens if and
when the patient is going
through a condition called
obstructive lung disease
obstructive lung disease is
where there is some airway
obstruction that's happening
and it causes an increase
in the resistance you can
imagine that and that's
called air trapping air is
there but it's not let go,
so it's obstructed. So that
means FEV1 can decrease,
pretty much you will expect
it to decrease and that's
decreased FEV1 because of
increased airway resistance
and this ratio I
mentioned is very
important that is
also decreased, okay.
Alright, so what are
the factors that are
decreased in obstructive
lung diseases such as
we have some examples
here bronchitis chronic
bronchitis asthma emphysema
etc fev1 is decreased
that's point number one
fev1 by fbc is decreased
point number two both
important points and
it's hard for them to
exhale quickly due to
increase in in airway
resistance now there
is one more important
parameter residual volume
is increased residual
volume is increased
excuse me so because it's
air is trapping inside
okay so more and more a
volume of air is trapped
and residual settle now
restrictive lung disease
which is like the opposite
story of obstructive there
here it is not obstructed
it's no obstruction but
it's restricted it's not
able to the compliance of the
lung is reduced not
compliant enough it increases
the stiffness of the lung
and lung and limits its
expansion so what does
this happen when does this
happen in patients with
decreased lung compliance like
pulmonary embol fibrosis
excuse me pneumonia and
pulmonary edema what do you
see decreased FEC which is
not different from the
other one at least a whole
lot so FEV1 is relatively
large in comparison okay
FEC is decreased in both
obstructive and restrictive
but key difference is FEV1
is relatively large in
comparison that is the
FEV1 by FEC ratio cannot be
higher than normal wow okay
so that's another key point
and this is because it's
easy for a person with a
restrictive lung disease
to breathe out then breathe
out quickly it's it's easy
to breathe out quickly
because of the high elastic
recoil of the stiff lungs
and here the residual
volume goes down not up
because in obstructive what
did we see residual volume
goes up so these are key
distinct very distinguishing
factors here you go re
-emphasizing it normal
obstructive and restrictive
right you're already seeing
it even the first second
is FEV1 the entire vital
capacity force vital capacity
okay and in obstructive
this reduces okay Look at
the FEV1 from 4 to 1.3,
it reduces and then from
4 to 2.8, it reduces.
So, that's restrictive
lung disease.
Again, it's 4.0,
FEC is 5.0,
80%. 80% is what you
need to remember.
Although there are
guidelines with more refined
definitions, at this stage
it's good to know for you the
normal value is approximately
80 percent okay but this
can change with or decrease
with age and so on now
one accepted procedure to
allow two practice is to
so one accepted procedure
is to allow two practice
breaths practice blows and
then record three good test
breaths so the highest fvv1
and fvc from these three
breaths are often used and
this can be helpful for
testing you know bronchodilator
efficacy and reversible
airway obstruction and so
on you know if you have
to use if patient has to
use albuterol you know by
nebulizer or meter dose inhaler
this just can be carried
out to make sure things
will be working fine there
is no airway obstruction
they can breathe well etc
okay so again another
way look at this 4.0
1.3 2.8 5.0 3.1 3.1
so both are 3.1 both
the feces are reduced
but look at the numerator
1.3 and 2.8 let's
see how that works.
There you go.
COPD asthma. So this is
obstructive and this is
representative restrictive.
Look at what's happening.
The FEV1 is reduced in both
in both but COPD asthma
has greater fall in FEV1.
They have to face that.
FVC again it's a flip.
FVC is decreasing COPD
and asthma as well but not
as bad as fibrosis. In
fibrosis there's a little
greater decrease but
when you look at the big
picture, FEV1 by FVC, this
decreased significantly
in COPD but either it's
normal or slightly above.
That's fibrosis. And
functional restive capacity
changes contrastingly. It
increases in COPD, very
important, decreases in
COPD, very important, okay.
Okay, so forced expiratory
flow from a forced
expiration. So we saw, I
introduced this 25% to 75% rate
initially in a figure, so
the forced expiratory flow,
oops the forced expiratory
flow in that in that
range right range of volume
this is called F1 and look
at the numbers it kind of
follows the FEV1 pattern
but it's good to know this
okay so 3.1 3.5 errors
per minute 1.5 1.4 excuse
me and then 3.7 so the
greater decrease happens
with obstructive the others
are okay so so far is clear
so this table is important
for you to remember to
get a better idea okay so
in obstructive both the
fev1 and fec are reduced but
fev1 gets a bigger hit okay
and in fibrosis both fev1
and fec are reduced,
but FEC is even slightly
higher reduced, which makes
the ratio close to normal,
close to normal or
slightly even above,
and then FRC, you cannot
ignore or miss it,
okay,
right,
dead space, let's move
on, dead space, sorry
for the pause, what is
dead space, that's the
fourth major, you know,
aspect, objective,
dead space is the portion
of each tidal volume
that does not participate
in the gas exchange.
It's called wasted
ventilation and it's the
sum of two types of
dead spaces. One is
anatomic and the other
is anatomic and alveolar.
In other words,
there is ventilation
but there is no perfusion. Yes,
but there is
no perfusion.
What is the point?
Ventilation is there and
where is it? We will in
the next slide where the
dead space can be seen.
Again upon expiration
the air in the dead space
that is still that is
expired first before any of
the air from the alveoli
reaches the atmosphere.
All right if you look at
this tree right if you look
at the tree there is trachea,
there is bronchial and
so on so from the trachea
bronchi and bronchioles
and then terminal bronchial
and respiratory bronchial
and then alveolar that you
know that those regions
come now anatomic dead
space is the total volume of
the conducting airways from
the nose or mouth via the
pharynx and the trachea down
to the level of terminal
bronchial and is about to
about 150 ml on average
in humans now this is
responsible for conducting air
to the alveoli and
respiratory bronchial but they
don't participate in the
process of gastric change which
means they have alveoli
that's it if they don't have
alveoli there is no gas
exchange and look at here
alveolar depths they begin
so there is the scope
of um gas exchange and
deeper and deeper they
will participate significantly
they must participate
for all of us to have
good uh oxygenation
so here you see no alveoli
no alveoli it is just air
that's moving in and out and
we need that we need that
so but that's its role now
this is anatomical dead
space how do you measure the
anatomical dead space let's
see and the methodology is
called we need to move on
methodology is called Fowler's
method briefly it here
is the it change in nitrogen
concentration at the
expired in the expired air
after a single sudden deep
inspiration of pure 100%
oxygen that's assessed okay so
the I have the reference
here Guyton and Hall you can
study there I'll just briefly
say the first portion of
so after doing that deep
inspiration of pure 100%
oxygen it fills the entire
dead space with pure
oxygen some O2 also mixes
with the alveolar air but
they don't completely
replace this air so the
first portion of the expired
air comes from the dead
space regions of the
respiratory passageways, where
the air has been completely
reduced by oxygen.
So in the early part of the
data, only oxygen appears.
And then what happens, at that
time, nitrogen concentration
is zero, then when the
alveolar air begins to
reach the nitrogen meter, then
the nitrogen concentration
gradually rises as you
see in the figure nitrogen
concentration gradually
starts rising and then boom
at one point it plateaus
right after more air has
expired all the dead space
air um all the dead space air
has been washed from the
passages and only the alveolar
air remains so the recorded
nitrogen concentration
reaches a plateau level
equal to its concentration
in the alveoli and as shown
in the pink part here the
gray area here right it
represents the air that has no
nitrogen in it and is a
measure of the volume of dead
space air this is nitrogen
this is no nitrogen right
so okay now when you if you
were given the information
gray area and then pink
area and then gray area
and then the ev what's ev
ev is the total volume of
expert it then you should
be able to measure the dead
space volume, the anatomical,
all right. So this is about
this measurement. Let's
move on to the next thing,
next type of dead space.
That's alveolar dead
space. And look at the
alveolar dead space.
What's happening?
Alveoli that does not,
that are ventilated, but
they are not profused.
And they, and no gas
exchange can occur. Why?
They are ventilated, but
they're not profused. But
we absolutely want there
are other alveoli that are
ventilated and perfused
but these ones don't so
those that do not get
perfused even though they get
the air it's useless but
it is just sitting there
those are called the alveolar
dead space okay on the
left side is perfused
alveolos on the right side non
-perfused alveolos and the vd
on the top is anatomic now
we get a you know a better
picture ok let's move on
how do you measure the alveolar
and anatomical combined
dead spaces so that method
for former method we saw
only anatomical here
anatomical plus alveolar dead
space ok this method is called
Bohr method Bohr equation
it later followed by
Enghoff modification so Bohr
Enghoff method here tidal
volume is multiplied so Vd by
Vd equals partial pressure
of carbon dioxide of the
alveolar gas which can be
replaced by which is replaced
by Enghoff with arterial
PECO2 minus the PECO2
which is a PCO2 of expired
air divided by PECO2 now if
you do this math if you're
given those numbers and then
with the tidal volume you
should be able to detect
the dead space volume all
right so that's pretty much
and those are the main
points I wanted to cover and
And during early expiration,
again, only oxygen is detected.
And then subsequently,
oh, this is, we're
talking about the
nitrogen dilution, right?
Sorry about that.
So if you're given
the numbers, you
should be able to do
the math here. So do
understand and
remember this formulae.
I want to give an example
here, gray area, you know,
numbers. If the gray area
is, let's say, 30, okay,
and then the total volume of
expired air, it would be 500.
So this is 30, this is 500,
and then in the bottom, we
already told you the gray
area is 30, and then the
pink area will be 70. So if
you do the math, and then
you should get 150. Okay,
so that's the, what is that,
150 is the dead space volume.
But it's not hard and
fast, it has to be 150.
The dead space can increase
slightly with age and
most people with normal
distribution of airways
resistances, they will reduce
their expired end tidal
nitrogen concentration
to less than two and half
percent within seven minutes
so it depends on airway
resistance as well okay and
those with higher resistance
in their airways can
take longer than seven
minutes to remove all the
nitrogen and that's where
the pathological scenarios
come it depends on how
the airway resistance is okay
whether it is obstructive
or not obstructive that
can make the difference
All right,
let's see, let's summarize.
In summary, most of the
lung volumes and capacities
can be directly measured
using spirometry,
but one thing that cannot
be measured is residual
volume, and it can be measured
by other methodologies
that we talked about,
helium dilution, but before
that, body pletismography
and so on. And restrictive
and obstructive lung
diseases can be distinguished
by duration and volume of
expiratory air release.
Okay,
so typically, or in
general, we can say that
the pulmonary volumes and
capacities are usually
about 20 to 25% less
in women than in men.
And they are higher in large
and athletic people than
in small and asthenic
people. So, what do you see
here? Depending on individuals,
they're built, etc.,
it can change. So, we want
to keep that in mind when
we interpret, you know,
whether certain, you know,
whether the PFT function
tests are normal or abnormal.
Let's see if, oh,
here's a quick
quiz. You can, you
can try it, right?
So you can ask yourself,
what is this? What is
this? This is tidal volume,
inspiratory tidal volume,
and what is this? This
is expiratory tidal
volume, and what is this?
This is inspiratory reserve
volume, and this is, and
it goes on. Then this
whole thing, right, this
whole thing is vital
capacity, and the inspiratory
capacity, and so on.
So it is just,
this is important,
the volumes and capacities,
there is a good
chance questions
will come, it's not a surprise,
not only in school exam in
boards as well, I would say.
So please do
understand, sketch it in
your hand if possible,
in a piece of
paper or using some
apps and so on.
You people are extremely
smart with various
gadgets so you can use
anything but do try to
practice you know the
different ways so you
will get a better
retention of information.
Okay so let's see what else
we saw we tried to understand
what they are and we gave
some numbers to them too
and there are times when
it can fall, FRC can fall
and spirometry methodology
you spirometry whole body we
saw and then this formula
try to practice but these
things are more important
FVC force vital capacity FEV1
by FVC why is it important
because it's pathologically
important pathologically in
a patient with obstructive
lung disease FEV1 reduces
pathologically FVV1 by
FVC ratio reduces and then
residual volume increases.
Three distinctions. Opposite
happens here with the
residual volume decreases
in restrictive lung diseases
like pneumonia or pulmonary
edema fibrosis you know and
so on. So FVC decreases but
FVV1 does not decrease. It
does decrease in obstructive
but it does not decrease
explicitly in restrictive.
It may slightly even go up
depends so but overall RV
decreases and we saw these
things we saw in the first
second what happens and then
that's you know these are
examples right typically
it's not hard and fast
for every single in normal
individual is 80 but it's an
average we have taken and here
the ratio decreases FVV by
FVC and then here slightly
it's close to normal or
slightly higher in right as we
saw okay this table also
will help you understand what
is more important in which
context right we saw this
and then that's this okay
let's please try to understand
the concept and then remember
the you know methodology
to measure all right
that's pretty much it if
there is any if there are any
questions. These are learning
objectives. Here are sample
questions for you all.
ScholarRx, you
have two ScholarRx
and then I have
a few books here.
So use your NYIT login
and go and access
these books, case files,
where you can have
a better understanding
of these cases.
And then certainly
there are board
prep materials you
already may know.
You know USMLE or UWorld
and we have this comeback
and so on but at the back
of books also the ScholarRx
there can be questions.
Guyton Hall is a good book
there is a newer edition
now 14th and 15th editions
both are good 15th is newer
and that's pretty much
it so any questions please
feel free to email me
hope things are as clear as
possible have a good book